FEDERAL HR SPECIALIST, BENEFITS OFFICER, GS-14 (RETIRED) Summary

Mr. Pearson is a Federal Human Resources (HR) professional with over 25 years of demonstrated success with significant experience in Federal Benefits and Retirement. He possesses extensive knowledge of federal government regulations such as they relate to Retirement, Benefits, Personnel, and Payroll. Mr. Pearson has spent the last 6 years of his career supporting the Department of the Army as a Federal Benefits and Retirements Specialist. He provides full counseling to employee for benefits and has extensive knowledge processing Retirement applications.

Highlights

- Hiring and retention
- Compensation/payroll
- Employee relationsRegulatory compliance
- Innovative
- Benefits administrator
- Off-boarding

- Personnel records maintenance
- Training and development
- New hire orientation
- Exceptional interpersonal skills
- Telephone communications

Experience

Federal HR Specialist, Benefits Officer, GS-14 (Retired)

December 2008 to April 2013 Department Of Army, Civilian Senior Leader Management Office (CSLMO) - City, STATE

- Provided technical advice and assistance to senior level management officials within the Department of the Army on all matters regarding Retirement, Benefits and Entitlements.
- Utilized comprehensive knowledge of the Civil Service Retirement System (CSRS), Federal Employees Retirement System (FERS), the Thrift Savings Plan (TSP) and the effects of social security contributions on the retirement/survivor annuities.
- Provided authoritative guidance on other Federal Benefits programs such as Federal Employees Health Benefits (FEHB), Federal Employees Group Life Insurance (FEGLI), Flexible Savings Account (FSA), Federal Employees Dental and Vision (FEDVIP), and the Federal Long Term Care Insurance Protection (FLTCIP).
- Conducted on-boarding and exit interviews with newly appointed/hired Executives and Senior Officials.
- Computed all annuity estimate requests, as well as processed and provided counseling for all retirement (voluntary and discontinued service), death, and disability applications for senior level management officials within Army around the world.
- Advised and counseled individual employees on Retirement coverage, Eligibility and Benefits under CSRS and FERS, discontinued service annuities, associated health benefits, and life insurance options.
- Coordinated with contacts within Department of the Army, and other agencies including Social Security Administration (SSA), Office of
 Personnel Management (OPM), and State employment commissions to ensure that current information was available to the retiree, survivor,
 and the dependents concerning rights privileges and benefits.
- Provided separation counseling for the mass exodus of political appointees who electively resigned, retired or who were not asked to stay
 on-board with the new administration.
- Conducted internal training for Staffing Specialists regarding correct retirement coverage determinations and determining creditable service.
- Provided training that included determining eligibility for other benefits such as FEHB, FEGLI, TSP, FSA, FEDVIP and Phased Retirement.
- Developed and presented a curriculum to conduct periodic briefings to Army executives and senior professionals on their Federal Retirement and Benefits.

Supervisory HR Benefits Specialist (GS-13/)Deputy Program Manager

October 2005 to December 2008 Department Of Defense Education Activity (DoDEA) Headquarters (HQ) - City, STATE

Supervisory HR Benefits Specialist (GS-13/)Deputy Program Manager 11/2007 â€" 12/2008

- Served as the Deputy Program Manager for the DoDEA HQ Benefits Unit, responsible for the management and administration of the Federal retirement and benefits programs.
- Supervised a staff of five employees as the Lead Benefits Specialist.
- Monitored and reported on the status and progress my work to ensure my supervisor was aware of individual work accomplishments, problems, and individual or Unit training needs.
- Calculated annuity estimates and processed retirements, voluntary, discontinued service, death and disability applications assigned to me.
- Processed civilian and military deposit application requests.
- Provided counseling to retiring and separating employees regarding their federal benefits and retirement.
- Provided expert technical guidance with interpretation of laws, regulations and policies related to employee Benefits.
- Provided authoritative advice and guidance to management on employee benefit issues and HR policies and procedures as they interrelate with and are impacted by employee benefits programs.
- Developed and issue policies, instructions, and standard operating procedures for the DoDEA employee benefits program.
- Prepared responses to retirement and benefits related Congressional inquiries.

Lead Federal HR Benefits and Retirement Specialist, GS-13 10/2006 â€" 11/2007

• Served as acting Chief of the Benefits Unit during my supervisor's absence from December, 2006 through May of 2007 performing the supervisory function for the Benefits Unit and staff.

- Processed retirement applications such as voluntary, discontinued service, as well as death and disability claims in accordance with OPM's
 guidelines and procedures.
- Provided expert technical guidance and interpretation of laws, regulations and policies related to employee benefits.
- Provided authoritative advice and guidance to management on employee benefit issues and human resources policies and procedures as
 they interrelate with and are impacted by employee benefits programs.
- Developed and issue policies, instructions and standard operating procedures and manuals for the employee benefits programs throughout DoDFA
- Prepared responses to retirement and benefits related Congressional inquiries.
- Represented DoDEA in meetings and conferences, such as the OPM Benefits Officer meetings, DoD Benefits Officer meetings.

Federal HR Benefits and Retirements Specialist, GS-12 10/2005 â€" 10/2006

- Worked a special project involving the Federal Erroneous Retirement Coverage Corrections Act (FERCCA).
- •Reviewed employee official personnel records in order to make technical determinations in regards to correct retirement coverage determination.
- Developed internal procedures in accordance with law, regulation and OPM guidance on the determination of coverage errors, employee notification and correction of official personnel records.
- Conducted in-house training for the DoDEA HQ Benefits Unit staff on the processing of benefit elections, retirement application processes, FERCCA errors, and elections.
- Assigned processing of current retirements, death and disability applications, annuity estimate requests, deposit and redeposit applications.
- Counseled employees on information regarding CSRS/FERS annuities; continuation of FEHB and FEGLI.

Federal HR Benefits and Retirement Specialist, GS-13

December 1998 to April 2004 Defense Human Resources Agency(DHRA), Civilian Personnel Management Services(CPMS) - City, STATE

- Served as an adviser and trainer on retirement and benefits issues providing policy guidance to the DOD human resources community.
- Provided recommendations to resolve identified issue or problem in accordance with the laws or regulations governing such benefit issues;
 interpreting regulatory guidance governing the processing procedures related to employee retirement and benefits Conducted comprehensive training on a basic and advanced level in all areas of benefits.
- Subject material included training on the civil service retirement systems (CSRS and FERS), determining creditable service, retirement
 coverage determinations, Non-appropriated Fund Instrumentality (NAFI), TSP, Social Security, FEHB and FEGLI programs.
- Conducted employee pre-retirement seminars for prospective retiring employees.
- Developed and prepared revisions of reference guides, and information sheets pertaining to employee benefits for use at all levels within the DOD employee and personnel community.
- Served as Internal consultant on the Professional Liability Insurance (PLI) Program, and on FEHB and FEGL issues.

Personnel Management Specialist, GS-11

December 1991 to December 1998 HQDA, Personnel & Employment Services-Washington - City, STATE

- Served as lead retirement counselor for Headquarters, Department of Army (HQDA) Employees, including the Senior Executive Service (SES), counseling employees on benefit issues such as FEHB, FEGLI, TSP, CSRS, FERS, and Medicare.
- Calculated projected retirement estimates for inquiring employees.
- Processed retirement applications for serviced employees.
- Counseled family members through the application processes.
- Calculated military service deposits for employees wanting to make a deposit for any creditable prior military service.
- Calculated deposit and redeposit amounts for employees wanting to make these payments for creditable civilian service.
- Tasked with reviewing serviced employee records for correct retirement coverage determinations.
- Recorded a pre-retirement seminar video to be distributed to HQDA field agencies to be used for viewing by employees.
- Conducted on site pre-retirement seminars for employees.

Education

High School Diploma: Business Administration Pensacola Christian College - City, State, USA Additional Information

- April 30, 2009 Received the Department of Army Commander's Award for Civilian Service commending me for providing exemplary service for transitioning Department of Army Senior Executives after the change in Presidential Administration.
- June 2002 Was awarded the Meritorious Civilian Service Award by the Defense Civilian Personnel Management Service for providing professional and compassionate support to the families of those injured and killed during the attacks on the World Trade Center and the Pentagon on September 11, 2001.
- Had a SECRET clearance with Department of the Army.

Skills

Proficient with HRIS systems (Oracle), Microsoft Word, Excel, PowerPoint and Outlook. Also proficient with retirement calculation software, GRB and FRB.